<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>osa1.net - Posts tagged en</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/tags/en.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="http://osa1.net" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/tags/en.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Ömer Sinan Ağacan</name>
        <email>omeragaca@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Parametric polymorphism and unboxed representations</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-10-09-parametric-polymorphism-and-unboxed-repr.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-10-09-parametric-polymorphism-and-unboxed-repr.html</id>
    <published>2013-10-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post was written 5 months ago – I just found it in my Github Gist archive and realized it’s not published. I’m publishing it now.</p>
<hr />
<p>It’s just occurred to me that we can’t have parametric polymorphism for unboxed values, unless that unboxed values share same layout in memory, or you duplicate polymorphic definition for each instance. This may be obvious for most of you but I just realized this while working on a Java project and found it interesting.</p>
<p>I think this is also the reason why we can’t instantiate generics in Java with primitive types.</p>
<p>Here’s an explanation:</p>
<p>Let’s think this C++ code:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode cpp"><code class="sourceCode cpp"><span class="kw">struct</span> test2
{
  <span class="dt">int</span> a, b;
  test2(<span class="dt">int</span> a, <span class="dt">int</span> b) : a(a), b(b) {}
};

<span class="kw">struct</span> test3
{
  <span class="dt">int</span> a, b, c;
  test3(<span class="dt">int</span> a, <span class="dt">int</span> b, <span class="dt">int</span> c) : a(a), b(b), c(c) {}
};

<span class="dt">void</span> f2() {}

<span class="kw">template</span>&lt;<span class="kw">typename</span> T&gt;
T f3(T t)
{
  t.a = <span class="dv">20</span>;
  <span class="kw">return</span> t;
}

<span class="dt">int</span> main()
{
  test2 t2(<span class="dv">1</span>, <span class="dv">2</span>);
  test3 t3(<span class="dv">1</span>, <span class="dv">2</span>, <span class="dv">3</span>);
  f3&lt;test2&gt;(t2);
  f3&lt;test3&gt;(t3);
  <span class="kw">return</span> <span class="dv">0</span>;
}</code></pre>
<p>The key thing to realize here is that I’m passing parameter by value, ie. values are copied to function stack frame. But this function is still polymorphic on parameter type. This is possible in C++ because for each distinct instance of <code>f3</code>, a specialized code will be generated. To observe this, I put a breakpoint to that <code>f3</code> function and looked to disassembly output.</p>
<pre><code>        18	T f3(T t)
0x400af6  &lt;+0x0000&gt;         push   rbp
0x400af7  &lt;+0x0001&gt;         mov    rbp,rsp
0x400afa  &lt;+0x0004&gt;         mov    QWORD PTR [rbp-0x10],rdi
        19	{
        20	  t.a = 20;
0x400afe  &lt;+0x0008&gt;         mov    DWORD PTR [rbp-0x10],0x14
        21	  return t;
0x400b05  &lt;+0x000f&gt;         mov    rax,QWORD PTR [rbp-0x10]
        22	}
0x400b09  &lt;+0x0013&gt;         pop    rbp
0x400b0a  &lt;+0x0014&gt;         ret</code></pre>
<p>And this is for second call:</p>
<pre><code>        18	T f3(T t)
0x400b0b  &lt;+0x0000&gt;         push   rbp
0x400b0c  &lt;+0x0001&gt;         mov    rbp,rsp
0x400b0f  &lt;+0x0004&gt;         mov    rdx,rdi
0x400b12  &lt;+0x0007&gt;         mov    eax,esi
0x400b14  &lt;+0x0009&gt;         mov    QWORD PTR [rbp-0x20],rdx
0x400b18  &lt;+0x000d&gt;         mov    DWORD PTR [rbp-0x18],eax
        19	{
        20	  t.a = 20;
0x400b1b  &lt;+0x0010&gt;         mov    DWORD PTR [rbp-0x20],0x14
        21	  return t;
0x400b22  &lt;+0x0017&gt;         mov    rax,QWORD PTR [rbp-0x20]
0x400b26  &lt;+0x001b&gt;         mov    QWORD PTR [rbp-0x10],rax
0x400b2a  &lt;+0x001f&gt;         mov    eax,DWORD PTR [rbp-0x18]
0x400b2d  &lt;+0x0022&gt;         mov    DWORD PTR [rbp-0x8],eax
0x400b30  &lt;+0x0025&gt;         mov    rax,QWORD PTR [rbp-0x10]
0x400b34  &lt;+0x0029&gt;         mov    edx,DWORD PTR [rbp-0x8]
        22	}
0x400b37  &lt;+0x002c&gt;         pop    rbp
0x400b38  &lt;+0x002d&gt;         ret</code></pre>
<p>So what happened here is two new functions is generated from the definition, one with type <code>test2 f3(test2)</code> and one with type <code>test3 f3(test3)</code>. This gives a great opportunity, for instance, we can have this function:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode cpp"><code class="sourceCode cpp"><span class="ot">#include &lt;iostream&gt;</span>

<span class="kw">template</span>&lt;<span class="kw">typename</span> T&gt;
T someFun(T arg1, T arg2)
{
  <span class="kw">return</span> arg1 + arg2;
}

<span class="dt">int</span> main(<span class="dt">int</span> argc, <span class="dt">const</span> <span class="dt">char</span> *argv[])
{
  std::cout &lt;&lt; someFun&lt;<span class="dt">int</span>&gt;(<span class="dv">1</span>, <span class="dv">2</span>) &lt;&lt; std::endl;
  std::cout &lt;&lt; someFun&lt;<span class="dt">float</span>&gt;(<span class="fl">1.4</span>, <span class="dv">2</span>) &lt;&lt; std::endl;

  <span class="kw">return</span> <span class="dv">0</span>;
}</code></pre>
<p>..which is impossible to have in Java, without manually overloading the method definition.</p>
<p>(An off-topic but interesting note: I was expecting <code>SP</code> to be set here, but here it’s not set. I think the reason is that the compiler is clever enough to see there is no recursive calls, so no need to set <code>SP</code>, when I added a dummy function call in the middle of <code>f3</code>, <code>SP</code> is got set)</p>
<p>So in a way, C++ generics are gives us the most general way for parametric polymorphism. For any type you instantiated the template with, it generates a specialized definition. And if that definition is accepted by type checker, you’re fine.</p>
<p>This also why we don’t need a template definition like <code>template &lt;class C : HasY&gt;</code>. Because that <code>HasY</code> information is completely redundant. If specialized code is well-typed, than it’s OK.</p>
<p>This is also one of the reasons why compiling C++ programs takes that long.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On proof automations -- part 3</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-23-proof-automation-3.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-23-proof-automation-3.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past several days I learned few things that changed my ideas about proof automation. See my first two posts about proof automation here: <a href="/posts/2013-09-11-proof-automation.html">#1</a> <a href="/posts/2013-09-17-proof-automation-2.html">#2</a></p>
<p>First, it’s really possible to use proof automation without first writing the whole proof. After started working on theorems defined on more complex languages, I realized one thing: Most of the cases of inductions/inversions are trivial to solve. Generally you only interested in one or two cases, while you have in total 20 cases. Why not use automation to eliminate 18 cases automatically? Proving that parts manually only makes it more obscure.</p>
<p>Second thing I learned is that automations like <code>auto</code>, <code>eauto</code>, <code>iauto</code> never perform <code>rewrite</code>, <code>subst</code>, case analysis(<code>inversion</code>, <code>destruct</code>, maybe others?) and induction. I think this is very important point, because this means that your proofs still have to resemble the structure of your non-automated proofs(i.e. structure of your terms). Which prevents your proofs from being too much magical.</p>
<p>Now let’s work on an example to see how some automation is good thing. I’ll prove progress property of STLC(simply-typed lambda calculus), as defined in <a href="www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/sf/">Software Foundations</a> chapter <a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/sf/Stlc.html">Stlc</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s an initial version without using any kind of automation.</p>
<pre class="coq"><code>Theorem progress_no_auto : forall t T,
     empty |- t \in T -&gt;
     value t \/ exists t&#39;, t ==&gt; t&#39;.
Proof.
  intros t T TD. remember (@empty ty).
  (* induction on typing derivation *)
  has_type_cases (induction TD) Case.
  Case &quot;T_Var&quot;.
    (* this case is impossible because vars are not well-typed in empty env,
       find a contradiction *)
    rewrite Heqp in H. inversion H.
  Case &quot;T_Abs&quot;.
    (* lambdas are values *)
    left. apply v_abs.
  Case &quot;T_App&quot;.
    (* well-typed applications should take a step *)
    right. destruct IHTD1. assumption.
    SCase &quot;t1 is a value&quot;. destruct IHTD2. assumption.
      SSCase &quot;t2 is a value&quot;.
        (* t1 should be a lambda *)
        inversion TD1; subst; inversion H. (* inversion on typing derivation of t1,
                                              most cases can be eliminated with inversion H,
                                              because t1 can only be lambda expression to be well-typed *)
        SSSCase &quot;t1 is tabs&quot;. eexists. apply ST_AppAbs. assumption.
      SSCase &quot;t2 can take a step&quot;.
        inversion H0. eexists. apply ST_App2. assumption. apply H1.
    SCase &quot;t1 can take a step&quot;. inversion H. eexists. apply ST_App1. apply H0.
  Case &quot;T_True&quot;. left. constructor.
  Case &quot;T_False&quot;. left. constructor.
  Case &quot;T_If&quot;.
    (* well-typed T_If can always take a step *)
    destruct IHTD1. assumption.
    SCase &quot;t1 is value&quot;. inversion H; subst.
      SSCase &quot;t1 is a lambda&quot;. inversion TD1.
      SSCase &quot;t1 is ttrue&quot;. right. exists t2. constructor.
      SSCase &quot;t1 is tfalse&quot;. right. exists t3. constructor.
    SCase &quot;t1 can take a step&quot;. inversion H; subst. right.
      exists (tif x0 t2 t3). constructor. assumption.
Qed.</code></pre>
<p>I leave comments to explain what’s going on. The point here is not to get shortest proof, but to show with some automation proofs could be more readable.</p>
<p>When you look to this proof you can realize that our interesting cases are:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>T_Var</code> case, in which we need to show that it’s impossible.</li>
<li><code>T_App</code> and <code>T_If</code> cases, in which we need to use induction hypothesis.</li>
</ul>
<p><code>T_Abs</code>, <code>T_True</code> and <code>T_False</code> cases are completely trivial and we don’t want to make our proof harder to write, read and maintain more.</p>
<p>Second thing to realize that, if you count <code>;</code> operator as a automation, then it makes me using automation even in that proof. In the case of <code>T_App</code>, I’m eliminating all cases of <code>t1</code>(because for <code>T_App</code> to be well-typed, <code>t1</code> can only be a lambda abstraction – other cases should be eliminated with contradictions) with <code>inversion H; subst.</code>. Without <code>;</code> operator, I would have to write this:</p>
<pre class="coq"><code>inversion TD1; subst.
SSSCase &quot;t1 is tvar&quot;. inversion H.
SSSCase &quot;t1 is tabs&quot;. eexists. apply ST_AppAbs. assumption.
SSSCase &quot;t1 is tapp&quot;. inversion H.
SSSCase &quot;t1 is tif&quot;. inversion H.</code></pre>
<p>and when the language gets bigger, more cases with just <code>inversion H</code> would follow.</p>
<p>Now here’s an automated version:</p>
<pre class="coq"><code>Theorem progress : forall t T,
     empty |- t \in T -&gt;
     value t \/ exists t&#39;, t ==&gt; t&#39;.
Proof with eauto.
  intros t T TD. remember (@empty ty). has_type_cases (induction TD) Case; auto.
  Case &quot;T_Var&quot;. rewrite Heqp in H. inversion H.
  Case &quot;T_App&quot;. right. destruct IHTD1...
    SCase &quot;t1 is a value&quot;. destruct IHTD2...
      SSCase &quot;t2 is a value&quot;. inversion TD1; subst; try (solve by inversion)...
      SSCase &quot;t2 can take a step&quot;. inversion H0; subst...
    SCase &quot;t1 can take a step&quot;. inversion H; subst...
  Case &quot;T_If&quot;. right. destruct IHTD1. assumption.
    SCase &quot;t1 is a value&quot;. inversion H; subst; eauto.
      SSCase &quot;t1 is tabs&quot;. solve by inversion.
    SCase &quot;t1 can take a step&quot;. inversion H...
Qed.</code></pre>
<p>IMO this proof is a lot more simple and readable. It eliminates all trivial cases and only leave us with interesting ones. And even in that cases we simply finished with <code>...</code> or explicitly running <code>auto</code>/<code>eauto</code>.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>TIL - Haskell 98 doesn't have principal typing property</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-20-til-haskell-principal-typing.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-20-til-haskell-principal-typing.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After hearing the term “polymorphic recursion” at <a href="http://fsl.cs.illinois.edu/index.php/Main_Page">FSL</a> meeting today, I just searched for it in Wikipedia(I never heard that term before). It’s explained with a Haskell code, with a note saying that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In Haskell, unlike for most other functions definitions, the type signature cannot be omitted.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>.. and that code is Haskell 98 compliant. For a long time I thought Haskell 98 has principal typing property – but apparently I was wrong. I wrote that in Haskell IRC channel and there were other people who were thinking same.</p>
<p>People at IRC channel also said that SML bans polymorphic recursion and have principal typing. Nice to know.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Quick rant: K Framework is broken</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-19-k-framework-broken.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-19-k-framework-broken.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="quick-rant-k-framework-is-broken">Quick Rant: K Framework is broken</h2>
<p>In this short rant I’ll demonstrate how K Framework is broken and how you can avoid the problem. If you don’t know what is K Framework or don’t use it, you probably want to ignore this post.</p>
<p>Let’s think this completely useless K module:</p>
<pre><code>module TEST

  syntax Exp ::= &quot;nilExp&quot;
               | return(Exp) [strict]

  syntax Val ::= &quot;nil&quot;

  syntax KResult ::=  Val

  rule nilExp =&gt; nil ... [nil]

endmodule</code></pre>
<p>and this TEST program:</p>
<pre><code>return(nilExp)</code></pre>
<p>what do you think this program has in K cell when it gets stuck? It’s not really hard to guess. Since we annotate <code>return(Exp)</code> syntax with <code>strict</code>, it’s argument gets evaluated according to our <code>nil</code> rule and then it gets stuck. At this point K cell will be:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;k&gt;
    return ( nil )
&lt;/k&gt;</code></pre>
<p>which may not be very surprising for you, but there’s something wrong going on here. In our syntax declaration we defined argument or <code>return</code> to be an <code>Exp</code>, but in the term in our K cell it’s <code>Val</code>.</p>
<p>At this point you can say that this is how heating/cooling works an there’s nothing wrong here but then we have another problem: there’s no way for the user to write rules that does exactly what heating/cooling rules do. In our example above you’d expect from strictness annotation to generate rules like this:</p>
<pre><code>rule return(E:Exp) =&gt; E ~&gt; return(HOLE)
rule V:Val ~&gt; return(HOLE) =&gt; return(V)</code></pre>
<p>but this is not a valid rule and it fails with the this error message:</p>
<pre><code>[Error] Critical: type error: unexpected term &#39;V:Val &#39; of sort &#39;Val&#39;, expected sort &#39;Exp&#39;.
        File: /home/omer/K/lua-semantics/test/test.k
        Location: (11,35,11,36)</code></pre>
<p>and what’s more confusing is that even though K generated rule somehow generates the term <code>return(Val)</code>, you cannot match it in your rules because this term is actually ill-typed:</p>
<pre><code>rule return(V:Val) =&gt; .
...
[Error] Critical: type error: unexpected term &#39;V:Val &#39; of sort &#39;Val&#39;, expected sort &#39;Exp&#39;.
        File: /home/omer/K/lua-semantics/test/test.k
        Location: (11,10,11,15)</code></pre>
<p>which means there’s no way for you to work on this term. This time you’re stuck :-p</p>
<p>We discussed this on k-user mailing list a bit but there isn’t really a solution – we only have a workaround. Here’s the reason of this problem(quoted from mailing list <a href="http://lists.cs.uiuc.edu/pipermail/k-user/2013-September/000475.html">discussion</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your grammar is only enforced during parsing.</p>
<p>After the definition is compiled, return is just a label that may be applied to a list of children.</p>
<p>In particular, the automatically generated cooling rule only puts a side condition that enforces IsKResult, which nil passes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Wow, this sounds like really broken to me. Anyway, only solution I could find to this is to add <code>Val</code> syntactic category to a member of <code>Exp</code> syntactic category. This is an obvious solution, but very bad one also. Because by having distinguished <code>Val</code> and <code>Exp</code> syntactic categories what I’m trying to do is to force my program to get stuck as soon as possible when something went wrong, instead of continuing evaluation and get stuck at a point where very very far from where the error actually occured.</p>
<p>Rest of this post is also sent to k-list mailing list and contains my ideas on implementing strictness annotations. These ideas may be wrong – I’m only a beginner K user.</p>
<hr />
<p>This is how I’d design strictness annotations(but I’m probably wrong since I’m just a beginner in K).</p>
<p>Let’s say I have this syntax:</p>
<pre><code>syntax Exp ::= P(Exp, Exp, Exp) [strict]</code></pre>
<p>for intermediate steps while fully evaluating this expression, I’d design the K framework so that these syntax and rules would be automatically generated:</p>
<pre><code>syntax K ::= P__rw_1(Val, Exp, Exp) [strict]
           | P__rw_2(Exp, Val, Exp) [strict]
           | P__rw_3(Exp, Exp, Val) [strict]

rule P(E1, E2, E3) =&gt; E1 ~&gt; P__rw_1(HOLE, E2, E3)
rule P(E1, E2, E3) =&gt; E2 ~&gt; P__rw_1(E1, HOLE, E3)
rule P(E1, E2, E3) =&gt; E3 ~&gt; P__rw_1(E1, E2, HOLE)

rule V:Val ~&gt; P__rw_1(HOLE, E2, E3) =&gt; P__rw_1(V, E2, E3)
rule V:Val ~&gt; P__rw_2(E1, HOLE, E3) =&gt; P__rw_2(E1, V, E3)
rule V:Val ~&gt; P__rw_3(E1, E2, HOLE) =&gt; P__rw_3(E1, E2, V)</code></pre>
<p>and then same rule generation scheme applies to <code>P__rw_1</code>, <code>P__rw_2</code>, <code>P__rw_3</code> too. In the end we’ll end up with:</p>
<pre><code>syntax K ::= P__rw(Val, Val, Val)</code></pre>
<p>and this would give the user full control of evaluation with strongly typed manner. (ie. without fighting with K framework parser)</p>
<p>(<code>strict[n]</code>, <code>seqstrict</code> etc. rules are specialized cases of this general strictness rule generation scheme)</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On proof automations -- part 2</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-17-proof-automation-2.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-17-proof-automation-2.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://adam.chlipala.net/">Adam Chilpala’s</a> <a href="http://adam.chlipala.net/cpdt/">Certified Programming with Dependent Types</a> has a great discussion on writing automated proofs and readability of proofs. Highly recommended. Chapter 16(page 319 on current revision).</p>
<p>I think one key thing to realize about interactive theorem proving is that there is no perfect, or maybe even good, solution to the problem of proof representation. Tactics help, but without automation tactic based proofs are just too fragile(every change in definitions implies changes in proofs) and verbose. But automated proofs are very hard to read, and it’s very hard to modify automated proofs for changes. CPDT book has a great example of this. Let’s think of this proof(I’ll skip the definitions, just think some simple arithmetic expressions language just like you could find in any elementary programming language theory book)</p>
<pre class="coq"><code>Theorem eval_times : forall k e,
    eval (times k e) = k * eval e.
Proof.
  induction e as [| ? IHe1 ? IHe 2]; [
    trivial
    | simpl; rewrite IHe1; rewrite IHe2; rewrite mult_plus_distr_l; trivial ].
Qed.</code></pre>
<p>And now let’s say you added one more constructor to arithmetic expression syntax. How to change this proof to adopt the changes? I don’t think there’s a way to do that without first writing the version without automation. And that brings us back to my first post.</p>
<p>I think the reason why I think too much about this stuff instead of writing some proofs is that I look for elegance and simplicity in my programs. And only if necessary I try to make my programs efficient(fast, small, whatever). After some simple trivial proofs that I did for learning I never found my proofs satisfactory. They are either very very long and repetitive or very hard to understand and modify. It’s very hard to find a sweet-spot in proofs that is not very repetitive and long and still possible to read and understand.</p>
<p>You can always apply methods you learned to make your programs easier to read and modify, like moving some code to a new function with a useful name and formal parameters etc. but in the case of proofs it’s also very hard to find what pieces are considered worthy to be a lemma and what would be useful name for it.</p>
<p>My ideas about proof automation is changed from “no way I use them” to “okay they can be very useful for eliminating repetition without adding obscurity to the proof” in one day. I’ll continue writing Coq proofs for while and probably add new posts on this topic later.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>On proof automations</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-11-proof-automation.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-09-11-proof-automation.html</id>
    <published>2013-09-11T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While working with constructive systems, at the lowest level you can directly construct proof objects by writing programs. But for realistic scenarios, this is probably too hard to do. Coq and Idris like languages provide an alternative way to construct proof objects: tactics. Tactics provide a way to derive proofs in a way that is somewhat like informal proofs given in spoken languages. But theorems you’re trying to prove is already too complex, and in some parts, very repetitive.</p>
<p>That <em>tactics</em> Coq like theorem provers provide also help you construct proofs with some automation commands. For instance, you can apply same steps several times, until you prove some subgoals. Or you can search for a proof by applying some steps in different combinations.</p>
<p>What doesn’t make sense to me is that in general you cannot really use that automation methods before manually writing long and hard proof by hand and showing that your theorem is really a theorem and it indeed has some repetitive parts.</p>
<p>And at this point you’re probably better off leaving the proof as-is because replacing explicit steps with some magic commands(I’ll come to this point later) only makes the proof harder to read, without any other advantages.</p>
<p>I have similar ideas for <code>auto</code> tactic. What it does is that it searches for a proof by applying different combinations of <code>apply</code> and <code>intros</code> tactics(with some limitations – it only uses apply for hypothesis and hint database which you generate while defining inductive definitions).</p>
<p>Now my problem with <code>auto</code> is that you can only use it when you absolutely sure that your theorem is indeed a theorem – that is, it has a proof. And how can you know that your theorem is correct? The only way to know this is to write a proof for it. Now let’s say <code>auto</code> tactic fails, and when this happens it can’t really say anything. Why did it fail? It may be because your proof is actually too long and it searched for a while but couldn’t find a proof(you can specify search depth as an optional parameter of <code>auto</code> tactic). Or maybe your hint base is not good enough. Or maybe your theorem is not actually a theorem and you cannot prove it.</p>
<p>So both proof search tactics and repetition elimination tactics have this same common problem: you cannot know that they work before writing the proof itself. And automation generally makes the proof unreadable.</p>
<p>Adam Chilpala’s “Certified Programming with Dependent Types” book encourages that automated way of proving. You have that complicated theorem that you don’t even understand what it is saying? No problem, <code>crush</code> tactic(which is not standard, distributed with CPDT book) will prove it for you in one command.</p>
<p>I’m not saying that <code>crush</code> like tactics are necessarily bad and you shouldn’t use it. I’d probably use it in real world when I need a proof that <code>crush</code> can generate and I don’t have time or motivation to do it myself.</p>
<p>And repetition elimination tactics are useful when you have a syntax tree with 15 constructors and you’re proving some theorem that’s relevant with only one of that constructors – 14 subgoals can be easily proved by some clever use of <code>;</code> operator in Coq.</p>
<p>What I’m saying that is several things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Automated proofs can make proofs harder to read and most of the time you already need to have written the long proof to see that it has repetitive parts or at least it is provable. (certainly there are cases where you’ll find yourself trying to prove something wrong)</li>
<li>Once a long proof is written, there is little or no need to remove that proof and replace it with an automated version. (one reason to do that is to have same proof working even after some inductive definitions is expanded/changed)</li>
<li>Most importantly, <code>crush</code> like automation tactics are pure black magic and doesn’t really teach you anthing. As a hobbyist who self-study all this, I prefer learning the principles instead of scripts and magic commands and black boxes.</li>
</ul>
<p>For this reasons I’m trying to use proof automation as little as possible.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>MANTI - Prolog implementation in 515 lines of Haskell</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-31-announce-manti.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-31-announce-manti.html</id>
    <published>2013-07-31T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-07-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI">MANTI</a> is a pure Prolog implementation in 515 lines of Haskell. It’s only implements pure parts, meaning it doesn’t have cuts, IO predicates, non-pure arithmetic(<code>is</code> structures in modern Prolog implementation) or other structures that break logical reasoning of Prolog programs.</p>
<p>Here are some example Prolog programs that currently runs under MANTI: (you can find these in <code>tests/</code> folder in source repository)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/tests/einstein.pl">Einstein’s riddle</a> – also called Zebra Puzzle. You can see problem definition in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zebra_Puzzle">Wikipedia - Zebra Puzzle</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/tests/nqueens.pl">N-queens problem</a> (not that it takes some time to solve it for board bigger than 5x5, reasons for that slowness explained below)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/tests/zurg.pl">Escape from Zurg puzzle</a> - you can see a paper with definition of this problem <a href="http://web.engr.oregonstate.edu/~erwig/zurg/">here</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>My aim while writing MANTI was to make it as simple as possible, yet a complete Prolog implementation that is capable to solve some real problems. For this reasons, it doesn’t have arithmetic, list structures and list operations built-in. Instead, arithmetic is implemented using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peano_axioms">Peano definitions</a>, you can see the implementation <a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/tests/peano.pl">here</a>. List operations are also implemented in MANTI itself, you can see definitions <a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/tests/list.pl">here</a>. List syntax is nothing special, it’s just a syntactic sugar that destructs to ordinary Prolog functors(you can see parser for list syntax <a href="https://github.com/osa1/MANTI/blob/master/src/Parser.hs#L80">here</a>).</p>
<p>For these reasons(and probably others, for instance, unification and <code>not</code> connective are implemented in most inefficient ways possible), it’s very slow. Also, there’s no way to disable occurs check without recompiling MANTI.</p>
<p>It’s mostly done and I don’t think I’ll work more on that. I hope you find MANTI useful(for learning purposes or others).</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>ANNOUNCE: My first academic work is now open source</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-22-sqml-open-sourced.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-22-sqml-open-sourced.html</id>
    <published>2013-07-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-07-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our work at Ozyegin University with Prof. Baris Aktemur is now open source.</p>
<ul>
<li>Home page: <a href="http://srl.ozyegin.edu.tr/projects/subtypedQuotedML/">http://srl.ozyegin.edu.tr/projects/subtypedQuotedML/</a></li>
<li>Github repository: <a href="https://github.com/ozusrl/SubtypedQuotedML">https://github.com/ozusrl/SubtypedQuotedML</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you have trouble compiling/running it, please file an issue at Github page.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Non-local returns in functional programs</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-21-nonlocal-return-in-fp.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-21-nonlocal-return-in-fp.html</id>
    <published>2013-07-21T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let’s say we want to get nth visited element in depth-first traversal of a tree. Doing this is almost too easy in a language with statements(all imperative languages, some functional ones): Just run the depth-first traversal algorithm with explicit stack, and use <code>return</code> when you visit nth node.</p>
<p>In an expression language(Haskell, some Lisp languages) this is somewhat tricky.</p>
<p>Since I almost always prefer simplest possible solution of a problem, this would be my first attempt in a real-world situation:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode haskell"><code class="sourceCode haskell"><span class="kw">data</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a
    <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="dt">Branch</span> [<span class="dt">Tree</span> a]
    <span class="fu">|</span> <span class="dt">Leaf</span> a

<span class="ot">toList ::</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> [a]
toList (<span class="dt">Branch</span> bs) <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="fu">concatMap</span> toList bs
toList (<span class="dt">Leaf</span> a)    <span class="fu">=</span> [a]

<span class="ot">dfsNth ::</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Int</span> <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Maybe</span> a
dfsNth tree n <span class="fu">=</span> listToMaybe <span class="fu">.</span> <span class="fu">drop</span> n <span class="fu">$</span> toList tree</code></pre>
<p>One concern about this function may be that the complexity of list generation. It’s hard to predict complexity of this function, but traversing the whole tree just to get first element of it would be costly anyway.</p>
<p>But thanks to lazy evaluation, this function still not very bad. Because only required parts of the intermediate list will be generated. To see why you can do two things: 1) Just place some <code>Debug.Trace.trace</code> calls in <code>toList</code> function and see how many times a leaf node is visited and 2) evaluate this function by hand and observe unevaluated thunks.</p>
<p>Let’s just do the first one, since it’s easier:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode haskell"><code class="sourceCode haskell"><span class="ot">toList ::</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> [a]
toList (<span class="dt">Branch</span> bs) <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="fu">concatMap</span> toList bs
toList (<span class="dt">Leaf</span> a)    <span class="fu">=</span> trace <span class="st">&quot;leaf node visited&quot;</span> [a]

<span class="fu">...</span>

testTree <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Leaf</span> <span class="dv">1</span>, <span class="dt">Leaf</span> <span class="dv">2</span> ], <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Leaf</span> <span class="dv">3</span> ], <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Branch</span> [ <span class="dt">Leaf</span> <span class="dv">4</span> ] ] ] ]</code></pre>
<pre><code>ghci&gt; dfsNth testTree 0
leaf node visited
Just 1

ghci&gt; dfsNth testTree 1
leaf node visited
leaf node visited
Just 2

ghci&gt; dfsNth testTree 10
leaf node visited
leaf node visited
leaf node visited
leaf node visited
Nothing</code></pre>
<hr />
<p>Other solutions are still worth exploring. When I think of “returning in the middle of a function” in Haskell, I always think <code>Either</code>. It’s monad definition is a great fit for this:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode haskell"><code class="sourceCode haskell"><span class="kw">instance</span> <span class="kw">Monad</span> (<span class="dt">Either</span> e) <span class="kw">where</span>
    <span class="fu">return</span>        <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">Right</span>
    <span class="kw">Left</span>  l <span class="fu">&gt;&gt;=</span> _ <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">Left</span> l
    <span class="kw">Right</span> r <span class="fu">&gt;&gt;=</span> k <span class="fu">=</span> k r</code></pre>
<p>So when <code>Left data</code> used in monadic bind(<code>&gt;&gt;=</code>), second parameter just ignored and <code>Left data</code> is returned. Just like returning in the middle of a function in imperative setting, by ignoring rest of statements.</p>
<p>Using monad instance of Either, we can easily implement our function:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode haskell"><code class="sourceCode haskell"><span class="ot">dfsNth&#39; ::</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Int</span> <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Maybe</span> a
dfsNth&#39; tree n <span class="fu">=</span>
    <span class="kw">case</span> iter tree n <span class="kw">of</span>
      <span class="kw">Left</span> a  <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="kw">Just</span> a
      <span class="kw">Right</span> i <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="kw">Nothing</span>
  <span class="kw">where</span>
<span class="ot">    iter ::</span> <span class="dt">Tree</span> a <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Int</span> <span class="ot">-&gt;</span> <span class="dt">Either</span> a <span class="dt">Int</span>
    iter (<span class="dt">Branch</span> []) n     <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="fu">return</span> n
    iter (<span class="dt">Branch</span> (b<span class="fu">:</span>bs)) n <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">do</span>
      n&#39; <span class="ot">&lt;-</span> iter b n
      iter (<span class="dt">Branch</span> bs) n&#39;
    iter (<span class="dt">Leaf</span> a) <span class="dv">0</span> <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">Left</span> a
    iter <span class="dt">Leaf</span>{}   n <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="fu">return</span> (n <span class="fu">-</span> <span class="dv">1</span>)</code></pre>
<p>It works exactly like our first implementation, but without generating an intermediate list.</p>
<h2 id="exceptions-and-either-monad">Exceptions and Either monad</h2>
<p>If I were using OCaml, I’d probably implement this function using an exception.</p>
<pre class="sourceCode ocaml"><code class="sourceCode ocaml"><span class="kw">exception</span> <span class="dt">NonLocal</span> <span class="kw">of</span> <span class="dt">int</span>

<span class="kw">type</span> &#39;a tree =
  | <span class="dt">Branch</span> <span class="kw">of</span> (&#39;a tree) <span class="dt">list</span>
  | <span class="dt">Leaf</span>   <span class="kw">of</span> &#39;a

<span class="kw">let</span> dfs_nth tree n =
  <span class="kw">let</span> <span class="kw">rec</span> iter tree n =
    <span class="kw">match</span> tree <span class="kw">with</span>
    | <span class="dt">Branch</span> [] -&gt;
        n
    | <span class="dt">Branch</span> (b :: bs) -&gt;
        iter (<span class="dt">Branch</span> bs) (iter b n)
    | <span class="dt">Leaf</span> a -&gt;
        <span class="kw">if</span> n = 0 <span class="kw">then</span> raise (<span class="dt">NonLocal</span> a) <span class="kw">else</span> n - 1
  <span class="kw">in</span>
  <span class="kw">try</span>
    iter tree n;
    <span class="dt">None</span>
  <span class="kw">with</span>
    | <span class="dt">NonLocal</span> a -&gt; <span class="dt">Some</span> a</code></pre>
<p>An interesting thing to realize here is that this solution is very similar to our Haskell solution. In Haskell, Either is an instance of <code>MonadError</code>:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode haskell"><code class="sourceCode haskell"><span class="kw">instance</span> <span class="dt">Error</span> e <span class="ot">=&gt;</span> <span class="dt">MonadError</span> e (<span class="dt">Either</span> e) <span class="kw">where</span>
    throwError             <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">Left</span>
    <span class="kw">Left</span>  l <span class="ot">`catchError`</span> h <span class="fu">=</span> h l
    <span class="kw">Right</span> r <span class="ot">`catchError`</span> _ <span class="fu">=</span> <span class="kw">Right</span> r</code></pre>
<p>This means if you replace <code>Left</code>s with <code>throwError</code> (just like <code>raise</code> in OCaml code), you have a similar solution with OCaml.</p>
<p>This doesn’t mean exceptions are same thing as Either types in functional programming. There are just too many differences that I won’t delve into in this post. With an exception, you can return from arbitrary deep contexts(ie. function calls), which is not easily possible with Either types. This is why exceptions sometimes referred as <em>non-local returns</em>.</p>
<p>We discussed this stuff over OCaml IRC channel, and smart people over there gave me some really good insights about non-local returns and exceptions. I’ll probably delve into details in another blog post. I’m especially interested in functional solutions that we can have in Haskell.</p>
<p>For the curious, for now I’ll just leave these two links here: (I haven’t read that links yet, but they’re probably related)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://ocaml.janestreet.com/?q=node/91">https://ocaml.janestreet.com/?q=node/91</a></li>
<li><a href="http://functional-orbitz.blogspot.se/2013/01/introduction-to-resultt-vs-exceptions.html">http://functional-orbitz.blogspot.se/2013/01/introduction-to-resultt-vs-exceptions.html</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Several other ideas also discussed at IRC channel, some of them were using delimited continuations, or passing a handler function as parameter and just calling it instead of raising an exception. I’ll continue investigating this stuff later.</p>
<p>I also came across this <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6915701/is-non-local-return-in-scala-new">StackOverflow post</a> that explains how Scala’s non-local returns implemented as exceptions internally. Interesting stuff.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Apparently I'm not going to Jane Street</title>
    <link href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-16-jane-street-interview-2.html" />
    <id>http://osa1.net/posts/2013-07-16-jane-street-interview-2.html</id>
    <published>2013-07-16T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-07-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had written about my first interview experience <a href="http://osa1.net/posts/2013-06-20-first-interview-jane-street.html">here</a>. After that interview, we did two more interviews with Jane Street, the last one was done yesterday.</p>
<p>Today I’ve got an email saying that I’ve failed.</p>
<p>I won’t write about last two interviews because I’m asked to not to write about questions.</p>
<p>Now I’m looking for Haskell jobs for my last internship and I just applied to Galois. I’ll keep posting updates here. Wish me luck.</p>
<p><em>EDIT: I got response to my job application email from Galois, saying that they would not be able to sponsor me for my visa application. Which means I’m still looking for jobs.</em></p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
